[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine online at computer.org software
at collide we know end users are it
admins most significant untapped
resources and key to solving the most
challenging to fix security issues
including instructing developers to set
passphrases on unencrypted ssh keys
finding plaintext two-factor backup
codes and teaching end users how to
store them securely
convincing employees to uninstall evil
browser extensions that may sell their
browser history
visit collide.com se radio to sign up
today that's
kolide.com
sc radio
enter your email when prompted to
receive your free collide gift bundle
after trial activation
you can try collide with all its
features on an unlimited number of
devices for free for 14 days no credit
card required
try it out at collide.com sc radio
this is jeremy jung for software
engineering radio today i'm joined by
uma chingunde she's the vp of
engineering at render and she previously
managed a team responsible for compute
at stripe
before that she was an engineer and
manager at vmware uma welcome to
software engineering radio thank you so
much for having me
so today i thought we could talk about
the experience of building a platform as
a service
and so where i thought would be a good
place to start is maybe defining what
that actually means what is a platform
as a service and what problem is it
trying to solve
i think the the term itself has not
existed for as long as people realize it
has also been used in kind of like
different contexts
so to kind of share a little bit i think
you're going to talk about the ecosystem
so you have software as a service
and the way i think of software as a
service is when you're actually just
running software online without having
to download something to your local
system and so that's that software as a
service and then at the other end you
have infrastructure as a service and
that's most of the cloud computing
provider so for software as a service to
exist you actually first need
infrastructure as a service to exist
because that's what all sas companies
run on top of usually and then in the
middle is this kind of other layer that
has kind of been built on top of
infrastructure as a service which is the
platform as a service
so imagine you are a sas company and you
want
kind of like you know you end up either
internally building your own platform
which are then providing as a service to
all the other engineers at your company
or you are relying on a third party
platform
and that's kind of where companies like
render come in which is you are
providing a platform where you're
providing a certain amount of
abstraction like essentially software
development abstractions for like you
know building your code writing your
code usually using open source
components building on top of github or
gitlab or similar and then having some
sort of like you know standard
components such as like an ability to
deploy your code run your code again as
as a service and that something that
provides all of those wrapped up is what
i like to think of platform as a service
so the additional thing that it's
providing that that differentiates it
purely from infrastructure as a service
in my view is infrastructure provides
kind of nuts and bolts so you know it
provides things like a layer of compute
or
you're getting memory and compute or a
virtual machine
or at the next layer and this is kind of
where maybe the boundaries get a little
blurred like are you getting a cluster
or you're getting a container but at
some level that's still like you know
all of it is infrastructure
and then things on top of that are the
next layer is platform
you mentioned infrastructure as a
service being provided by
companies like amazon and google
providing you virtual machines or maybe
providing you a way to run containers
and platform as a service would be a
layer of abstraction on top of that so
not working directly with those things
yes yes exactly that's more the way i
think of it as platform as a service is
the tools to develop your sas software
but that provide kind of a higher level
of abstraction and pure computer memory
companies that are running the big
infrastructure as a service products
like amazon like google
why don't you think that developers use
what they already provide like what is
it that they're missing
that has to be served by companies like
yours to kind of answer the question i
like to kind of you know go back a
little no doubt on the history of cloud
computing a bit and this kind of is
informed a little bit by the fact that i
used to work at vmware so vmware kind of
they were not the first but they were
like one of the major providers of
popularizing the concept of virtual
machines so before that you only had
physical servers or laptops or desktops
but like everything was like physical
they introduced this ability to kind of
slice up parts of your physical server
and create essentially virtual machines
so the ability to run independent
isolated systems within one physical
device and that became like virtual
machines and that kind of led to cloud
computing because now amazon and google
and microsoft could kind of you know
provide these virtual machines online
and so slowly everything kind of the
entire data center which used to be like
physical hardware became virtual and
essentially got moved to the cloud but
in that what happened was all the
complexity too got lifted and shifted so
you know the complex networks got lifted
and shifted everything was just moved
together to the cloud when you today go
to google or amazon or any of the cloud
providers in many ways it is not that
different an experience from buying a
physical server and racking and stacking
and kind of you know there is some level
of use that has been introduced because
it's all virtual you're not actually
going to a physical store and like
running cables there is that level of
abstraction but the concepts themselves
are still essentially physical
concepts virtualized with some basic
level of simplification added and now so
if you take that metaphor a little
further what developers engineers
builders or products need is more than
that they need the dev environment they
need a lot of other things on top of
just pure servers
if you kind of compress all of that into
one product that's that layer that we
are building
this layer that you're building on top
are you building it on top of an
existing cloud or are you running your
own servers and how did you come to that
decision
so currently we are building on multiple
clouds that is what we're doing the way
we came to this decision is that the
current the underlying cloud provider is
this sort of commodity at this point and
things like kubernetes give us enough of
an abstraction that we can actually
build on top of an existing cloud
provider and then also introduce on
physical data centers under the hood and
we have kind of experimented with it but
we don't we don't have full production
level systems running yet so that is
like you know part of the plan but it
isn't there yet these abstractions allow
us to actually like run on a particular
cloud provider and then create a similar
cluster and a different cloud provider
and then also then move that same
workload to bare metal eventually but
that's kind of how we're doing it how we
kind of came to the decision was i think
it was so this was before my time at the
start of life i've only been there a
little over a year but i kind of know
the history which is i think the
original thing was the core competency
that we're providing is this developer
experience is this platform so
the ideal goal was solve for that and
then work
like you know work down the stack
instead of trying to build from scratch
like why reinvent what has already been
done at the lower layers instead try to
build the differentiation at the higher
level than work back down
so it sounds like from what you were
describing is you're you're starting out
with
a software that can run on basically any
virtual machine on any server and you're
running on top of public clouds
with the sort of testing in the back
where you're trying to see like if we
needed to run our own servers could we
move those workloads over to them and so
maybe you get started running on these
public cloud providers and as you grow
then maybe you could shift to bare metal
to either for cost savings or for other
reasons exactly that's kind of where we
are there's many different reasons cost
saving would probably be the less
interesting one it would be kind of you
know providing options for our service
in places where the cloud providers may
not exist
something that has gonna become more
interesting in the more kind of you know
in the last few years has also been
regulatory reasons where a lot of
countries are introducing regulations
where they want companies wanting to
serve their citizens to kind of like you
know have a physical presence there so
there's many different reasons and so we
think that there will always kind of you
know be good reasons to explore that
space do you have any concerns about
these other cloud providers building
what you're providing like aws goes in
goes like oh let's see what render's
doing and we'll make our own version of
that i think for better or worse i think
that's
something that most sas companies have
to deal with i think you can probably
like between the three major cloud
providers you could actually credibly
always ask this question right like if
you're building on them can they in turn
build the same product and i think that
always exists and i think saying that
that's not a possibility would be kind
of naive but that being said
they haven't done it yet and i think
that's kind of you know why startups
have to exist and you could say the same
thing for like many other companies like
in fact this used to actually be a
relatively common question asked at
stripe which is like what if amazon gets
into payments like you know will they
take over our business and so far they
haven't and i think that's where i think
you have to be very clear about the
direction and the differentiation that
you are providing which is where kind of
it goes back to the origin which is
we're not immediately trying to go build
from bare metal our focus is developer
experience and the developer platform
and that doesn't yet exist and the plan
is to get really really good at that and
be the preferred place for all
developers to better yeah and i suppose
like you said it doesn't currently exist
so if they were to come onto the market
in a few years you would have a you know
x number of years head start as well
i think this goes back to kind of you
know like the differentiation and the
mode you want that head start you want
the stickiness where our users you know
have workloads on us have like you know
their startup working on us have really
like grown to trust us and have grown to
love our workflow enough that they would
seriously consider like you know a point
of friction to be forced to move to the
other place so we've talked a little bit
about how
render is a platform as a service to
allow developers to run their apps and
not have to worry necessarily about
specific virtual machines specific
containers and i wonder if you could
talk a little bit about how you're
running those applications you mentioned
kubernetes briefly earlier but i wonder
if you could elaborate a little bit more
on what's happening i can't go into too
many details just because that's a bit
of the secret sauce at a high level like
you know kind of like trying to answer
the question in as much detail as is
okay but without revealing too much i
think in this case kubernetes is more of
a tool it allows abstractions for us
like it allows us to abstract this layer
between virtual machines and user
workloads in a clean way which allows
like you know things like ease of
migration things like spinning up
additional clusters that's that's like a
primary thing and that's kind of why we
use it so i don't want to index too
heavily on oh that's the underlying kind
of you know mechanism it's a tool that
solves a purpose much like the way the
underlying cloud provider is solving the
purpose it's a way to kind of you know
build that abstraction at the really
really high level with the underlying
product is building this thing where
we're abstracting so when you as a user
don't have to think of your compute and
have to think about where you want to
run your service and where you want to
kind of you know you're not thinking
from a provisioning workflow so what
we're doing is we're creating an
abstraction where you're removed from
the provisioning workflow and instead
have to deal with the developer workflow
and that's really the gist of the
overall platform so you're thinking at
the level of writing code in github and
then like you know it's linked to your
render account and so you create a pr
and then you use preview environments or
similar and then you deploy your code
and it goes live
and the entire layer of the product is
actually just that which is like
managing this workflow i guess that's
kind of like the level that it's
possible to do it at uh without like you
know kind of drawing an architecture
diagram but we're kind of like
essentially shepherding the user's code
using their workflow instead of being
like okay now click on create a virtual
machine and now copy your code from your
desktop to or like you get report to
this place and now run it run the binary
there right like essentially just by
packaging all of that into the developer
workflow
like i guess in our initial email
conversation we talked a little bit
about being able to talk about the parts
that used open source or which you built
yourself and where you partnered with
other providers and i'm wondering like
out of those different pieces if you
could talk to as an example like oh
these are the things that we use that
are open source and these are the things
we decided we needed to build ourselves
i wonder if you could talk about a few
of those things yeah yeah i think one
example because it's somewhat recent
that i could talk about would be i think
because it's also like a differentiation
that we're providing is partnerships so
one thing that we did very recently is
we actually decided to kind of actually
we realized that enough of our users
were vulnerable to kind of like you know
security attacks or are mostly also like
the dots attacks and so it kind of
actually became kind of like an
interesting question for us which is do
we continue solving these either as
incidents like you know where this
happens and we mitigate it live which is
actually possible to do which is what we
were doing until that point do we use
what cloud providers provide
also as a service or do we use someone
independent or do we also like actually
just build the capability ourselves and
i think this was an interesting exercise
of a sort of like a build versus buy
model for us what we decided was that
this was enough of a problem or like if
you were successful this would become
enough of a problem that it would make
sense for us to become really good at
early but it was also not the thing
where
we would necessarily be differentiating
ourselves because our core is the
developer workflow and like providing
the best developer experience and being
the best platform to run on and there
are
companies that do this full-time as like
their core business and that's kind of
where we evaluated basically a few
different vendors including the cloud
providers themselves and then decided to
actually pick cloudflare as a vendor and
so all our user workloads everything is
behind cloudflare and that kind of gives
us this protection and then there were
some interesting discussions around
pricing which is like oh you know we are
paying for it do we pass that cost on to
our users or do we actually offer it as
a benefit and then we decided that at
least for now we will actually offer it
as a benefit so that it kind of goes
with the concept of viral platform and
so you shouldn't have to think about
individual components of the platform
and
this level of security and ddos
protection is part of the platform
basically like this makes the superior
platform but as a developer it's not
something you want to be thinking about
and so it's like baked into it directly
and i thought that was an interesting
exercise because as part of that we
actually rewrote the way traffic gets
routed to render and we actually have a
couple of really good blog posts on both
pieces of this which is picking using a
vendor for ddos protection and then also
the way we structured our anycast
networks any cases the way like you know
it's essentially how traffic comes in
and then gets distributed across and
those were kind of like interesting
architectural decisions that we made
over the last year so it sounds like in
this example
when people deploy an application
there's a lot of i guess bots and things
like that just trying to hit your
application that have no interest in
using it but are just wasting your
resources and
you made the decision that it's
important to have it but
there are other companies that are
either have
more people dedicated to it or it's a
problem they've been working on for a
while and so rather than you having your
team build a solution for that you
decided okay we'll let cloudflare handle
that for us yeah that's kind of exactly
the decision that we made and we've
actually had to make this a few
different times like another example was
like round metrics there's many
different platforms and vendors again i
think this is actually where we use a
mix of open source and also kind of a
bespoke vendor in this case use data doc
but then also for like kind of for
kubernetes because we use that so
heavily we actually use prometheus
because that's really a well understood
framework and it provides a good level
of abstraction but then we're also also
constantly
liking evaluating
other options so i think the benefit of
open source is there's always so many
different things that are evolving that
you know we can actually like pick and
choose and kind of you know as long as
you know we're willing to take the cost
of migrating from one solution to
another you can actually always be a
little ahead in what's being provided
and then because we're a platform
sometimes some of these decisions will
also get driven by what do our users
want are more of our users asking for a
certain type of integration this comes
up with third-party integrations a lot
so things like we have this concept of a
deploy to render button and we do that
we use this for like you know say say
you're like an open source project and
you want to kind of tie in your ability
to deploy that project to render
seamlessly and and so we will kind of
you know build that integration and
that's where often the decision making
goes which is which ones are popular in
particular communities and which ones
are getting traction and then based on
that and sometimes it will also actually
be determined by whether we ourselves
are users of that open source project we
ourselves are developers and the fact
that you know if something's appealing
to us or if we are seeing a gap in a
particular offering that's likely
something our users in turn will also
need so that goes into a lot of these
conversations
so in terms of deciding what to let open
source software handle or software as a
service handle you mentioned the
security like denial service you
mentioned logging and metrics and things
with datadog and prometheus but i'm
wondering
what are some things that you looked at
and you decided these things are our
core competency and we really do need to
build these ourselves that's a good
question i think things that we decided
on are actually anything that deals with
sort of like the look and feel of the
website you know so anything that or the
dashboard itself so like when you use to
enter the product anything that kind of
flows from that experience we kind of
own and build because the idea is that
that's kind of you know where you are
like you're using the product and any
sort of like interruption in that
experiences for a relatively small
startup like you know we're quite design
uh centric that way so you know we work
with designers we work with uh ux
engineers there's i think the difference
because i think is particularly in depth
tools or generally in in tools as a
space there may not be the same polish
and the same kind of attention to detail
being spent as you see in consumer apps
there has been a very conscious decision
to do that internally so anything that
kind of touches the products look and
feel or the developer experience itself
we are very conscious of owning and then
even like in the internals
anything that's part of like the
developer workflow even if we are using
open source components like kubernetes
kind of going back to that right it's we
try our best to like that abstraction
shouldn't leak out like you might know
that that's what we're using under the
hood because you're listening to this
conversation but if you're actually
using the product it's not like you're
not deploying thinking about kubernetes
right like you're just thinking about
deploying your code and having that be a
very clear separation is important the
part that's actually running the
applications may be based on open source
software like you mentioned kubernetes
but all of the not sure how you would
describe it but you mentioned developer
experience so maybe the part that the
user sees when like you said they go to
the website or they push their code and
then the the part that's maybe
taking that code and running the
workload that's all stuff that you wrote
internally and is i guess you could say
secret sauce of the company apart from
like the integration with it to the kind
of developer workflow
setting up the integration and then
the preview environments is another good
one where you know you can like actually
like have a have a pr kind of review
separately and that's i think one of our
actually differentiation features so
things like that that are like core to
that experience are like a big those are
the ones that we invest in i think maybe
another thing to think about is we are
kind of also like you know
experimenting with and also like
providing features that are like managed
databases is a good question where this
boundary becomes harder so we provide a
managed postgres as a product feature
and then we also are working on redis
manage traders and i think that's
managed databases is a very interesting
one because we are very careful about
because most kind of stateful apps need
a database and one wanted database we
don't want to have to manage the
database but then are we now getting
into the kind of managing tvs as a
product so that's where we're like
judiciously picking a couple of the most
common ones that people need and want
and then that's where you know the
constant user conversations and sort of
like the evolution of the roadmap comes
into play
so you mentioned the managing of
databases and i wonder like from the
perspective of a company who's
running a sas
is managing user databases is that the
sort of thing where you have to have a
bunch of dbas on staff and people who
you know would typically know how to
monitor the database and tune in things
like that you know they're just watching
all of your customers or what does that
that actually look like from your end i
think uh we're lucky again to be in a
you know in a kind of state where a lot
of that has
thankfully been automated but but it is
100 is one of those things where you
start going into more specialization so
it is like it does require people to
have a deeper understanding of the
underlying technology versus just gluing
components together so yes absolutely so
what we kind of have to do there is
build the tooling kind of in a monitor
monitor the databases manage them
upgrade them that's like a common thing
so it takes us immediately from not
having to worry about user state to like
you know we're always worrying about
user statement more at the metadata
level and this takes us to kind of a
known absolutely at the data level you
start having and that that introduces
complexity and a need for like you know
managing state at a different
layer
when you're talking about going from
like when you worked at stripe you were
managing compute so i i imagine that
it's sort of similar to running a
platform as a service except that it's
for an internal company and i wonder if
you could speak to how that compares to
running an actually public platform as a
service
yeah i like this question because it's
also one of the ways that i actually
describe render often to people like if
i'm talking to like uh former colleagues
from stripe or just like you know people
that are familiar or that have been a
work at other large sas companies which
is you know we're building render for
the broader public so the set of
constraints is very different for one
and they both have pros and cons with an
internal platform you have a captive
market right like you have a captive
audience who while captive are also
highly opinionated
and are not afraid of making their
opinions be known and then also
depending on the size i was i was there
from like around 800 employees to like
you know a few thousands so depending on
the size what you're running also just
becomes more and more critical so the
criticality of what you're running just
becomes so huge where you go from you
know running
production level but like moderately
critical workloads where an incident
while terrible isn't like you know like
isn't being tweeted about actively by
hundreds of users and then over time you
know scale so it is very much so the
kind of experiences you kind of have
this everything is kind of like much
more homogeneous
but feels higher stakes especially as
the company grows because you know you
are kind of you know in charge of it so
that's kind of like the both the pros
and cons of that you're like running
this uh internally you have a dedicated
security team that you're working with
you have all of these kind of
resources but then the stakes and
consequences are way higher
on the other side when you're building
for the general public it's just really
interesting because it's so much more
heterogeneous people are doing really
really interesting things on our
platform and are asking for really
interesting use cases and are you know
seeing interesting failure modes so it's
it's a completely different thing the
joy of that is you have a lot more room
to experiment and try and like you know
you're getting like entirely different
feedback loop but they're also like you
know not captive so you know they just
have like you know they're there but
they'll also leave and there isn't like
this kind of clear direct
path or like you know a road map for
instance no one's giving us this roadmap
from above and saying this is your
roadmap go build this that's for us to
actually do versus when you're building
an internal platform it's very very
clear like this is the company's goal
these are the companies products that
are the most important and this is what
you have to do there do to get them
there and like that's it and so what
that allows you is kind of you know it
allows more speed but at the risk of
actually like you know building things
that are less polished
because speed is like the biggest thing
because the underlying infrastructure
team cannot be the bottom like a product
company when you're building for the
public you you know your constraints are
that you can't just like give something
to people to try unless it's like you
know completely like actually ready and
it actually needs to be a fully fleshed
product it needs to be supportable
otherwise you'll start having incidents
but the use cases are so many more that
you can actually like do it in a much
more incremental way where we kind of
have the luxury of experimenting with
things like free tier that's something
that just doesn't make sense as an
internal platform like it is kind of
literally free so there is this tighter
loop with your users that you kind of
have as a public platform that as an
internal platform you kind of have a
very different set of incentives and
constraints but i do think that there's
a lot that you can kind of
borrow
and replicate in both realms one thing
i've kind of leaned
leaned on and tried to become better at
is this kind of you know listening to
users and like you know keeping that
feedback loop much tighter which i can
actually see
having like another skill would have
actually been already good even at a
larger company and then i think there's
a certain level of trigger and eye for
detail that internal platform teams have
because you know often the critical
nature of what they're running means
that everything has to be way more
detail that i'm trying to kind of you
know bring to our smaller team my pitch
is really like you know you're getting
like that grade of platform so if you
are as a developer like you know
starting out but you don't have access
to that internal infra team we are
trying to be that internal infra team
for you
yeah it's interesting that you mentioned
how
when you're doing internal
infrastructure the stakes are very high
and i can understand that in the case of
stripe right if people can't make their
payments then they're going to be upset
but i wonder like you were mentioning
how on the public side
wouldn't it seem like the stakes would
be just as high to your customers so i'm
kind of wondering how you reconcile that
i think the difference here is at our
stage like we're a series a company the
hope is that our our stakes are as high
very quickly as well right now though it
is that for us it's kind of like the not
all our eggs in one basket sort of thing
where like you know where one is like
you know for instance we already like
work with multiple cloud providers so by
nature of targeting somewhat different
businesses
we are operating slightly differently
where the economics of that did not make
sense or will typically not make sense
for a larger company like you'll find
very few larger companies working with
multiple cloud providers they usually
pick one and go go deep on them so
there's things like that that kind of
end up getting built in for us that give
us some built-in resilience and then i
think while the stakes are high across
the board like for us we have so many
different users that that kind of gives
us a different level of resilience but
the underlying point that you make is
absolutely true which is like you know
it is uh
the stakes are higher it's that to me
it's just more as a function of time and
stage rather if i understand correctly
when you are working for a company like
stripe and as it gets larger and you
know gets more funding more employees
inevitably more people rely on it and
your reliability needs to go up and of
course the end goal would be the same
for something like render but it's
very early days and that's always going
to be a gradual process yeah yes 100
when you are like the payments company
and you are in turn serving like you
know users
that are public companies that's just a
different level of stakes and when you
are a startup and your primary like your
primary users are at a different stage
as well the um other comment i thought
was interesting was you mentioned how
the constraints when doing internal uh
compute might
make it i don't know if you specifically
said that you might have to build things
slower was that right and i was
wondering if that's because you're also
responsible for more things because you
have more internal knowledge of the
different applications that are running
i think when i said that to kind of you
know clarify a little more i think what
can end up happening
is
at a larger company
i think what you end up doing is you can
actually
go
quite fast but you don't often have the
luxury of like finishing things or like
productizing internal infrastructure so
there's often like this journey where
internal infrastructure teams sort of
run as like service teams they are
providing services for the rest of the
company but they aren't quite able to
break through that next layer and also
act as like fully functioning product
teams so i guess like the difference is
that you're able to like deliver 80
of what your users need faster and but
then you likely never get to that last
ever then you're kind of perpetually
like you know dealing with like the
leftover of that last 20 so that can
kind of be actually like a frustrating
thing for internal infrastructure teams
versus you can't do that as a product
company because you always have to
provide your users with a very polished
product experience otherwise they just
won't use use you versus the larger
company they don't have a choice but
then you're often also just like working
with constraints such as like you know
team capacity and team priorities that
will be slightly different so i don't
think it's more like you go faster or
slower maybe that's the wrong
characterization it's kind of like
what's the level of finish that you uh
need to provide in both and i actually
do honestly think that most internal
infrastructure teams would better serve
their users if they were run more as if
they were external products but that
unfortunately doesn't tend to happen for
many different reasons yeah that makes a
lot of sense because if i understand
correctly when you're building for an
internal organization you could have a
you know an offering that works
providing real business value and people
are hosting their applications on it but
there's like little either developer
experience issues or maybe there's
occasional reliability problems and
people have to go in and deal with that
either in your team or from the
application team but maybe it can be
hard to get the people assigned to the
resources assigned to go like hey let's
solve this once and for all because it's
annoying but it's not stopping the
business
that's that's 100
exactly the thing so like an ongoing
thing that all large companies are like
migrations so there'll be like the
business critical migrations that will
happen but there won't be the less
critical ones it'll be like any large
team will just have like a pending
backlog of like oh yeah we want to
migrate to this like new framework this
new you know this better tool this
better thing but they will just like
never have the time or bandwidth to get
to it
and with the case of something like
render that's to the public if you
release a feature or an offering and it
has like kind of shaky developer
experience or it works 90 something
percent of the time then customers are
just going to go like i can't use this
yeah they're not going to deal with it
like an internal company might exactly
that's exactly the kind of constraints
and incentives i wonder also from the
perspective of
monitoring your platform as a service or
your internal teams at stripe is that
different monitoring internal
applications versus monitoring workloads
that are coming from you know who knows
where where you have no visibility into
your source and things like that i think
for the most part it looks similar but
then there's like similar vectors to
what we talked about earlier already
right we have to actively monitor for
people violating our terms of service or
like you know using our platform for
fraud or abuse or like you know using
our platform to be the source of
phishing or ddos attacks for other
people you don't have that problem with
an internal team because that's just not
going to be a problem so i think there's
a much bigger vector of misuse of an
external platform that you have to
monitor for putting safeguards against
than you do with an internal platform so
there's a kind of like a wild garden
versus like the general bazaar sort of
problem that you have how are some ways
you deal with the
unknown aspect of who's coming to use
your service whether it's for malicious
purposes or someone's trying to just tie
up your resources and not be like a
regular customer that sort of thing i
think that's where we basically i mean
all of this is monitoring and solved
like you know with different with all
the tools at our at our disposal so it's
it's sort of like you know so we have
the kind of the basic monitoring like
monitoring of all the critical
components monitoring of all the
resources monitoring user sign-ups to
the extent possible everything that's
automated and then other angle is like
you know there's an ongoing effort which
is like you know truly like never ending
which is like you know fraud and abuse
monitoring so that's again it's
automatable and actually this is not in
the sense that this isn't like not a
problem for companies like stripe it
just comes in at a different space right
there people are trying credit card
abuse and fraud so it's actually kind of
interesting where the same sort of tools
actually get used like stripe isn't like
manually verifying you know credit card
abuse it's it's similar you can like you
know programmatically monitor for like
you know people signing up you know for
fraudulent reasons or with like you know
stolen cards or for are using like
phishing attacks and stuff like that so
it's always like a mix of you know
automating that monitoring and like you
know automating action that you take for
the monitoring and then always having
the fallback for there is also like
sometimes like a manual element for a
lot of these things so the ceo of render
user actually was ahead of risk at
stripe so he is very familiar with uh
fraud and abuse and handling it and so
he'll often take like you know the the
front seat in these discussions because
he's kind of you know done it for this
axis and so it kind of you know it's
kind of interesting how much of that
translates and also how many of the same
tools we can use to detect fraud
another thing i thought we could talk
about is when you're building a platform
as a service or you're building an
internal compute team what type of
expertise are you looking for and is
that different than somebody who's
building a software as a service for
example i think
broadly i don't think they're that
different i think in tech
especially the landscape changes so
quickly that what you really want is
people
that are able to kind of be flexible and
learn new things quickly and like you
know kind of like an example like most
of the stuff that i learned isn't like
the relevant skill anymore like the kind
of you know the code that i originally
learned to program and just isn't like
useful like sure there are some places
still doing c plus plus but that isn't
mainstream i mean it's still a very
widely used language but that's not
today's startups
so i think in general you just want
people that are really good developers
have a lot of curiosity and have a lot
of kind of willingness and desire to
learn which usually kind of you know
goes with curiosity and humbleness so
you know not assuming that they have all
the answers and not kind of coming in
with the mindset that hey i am like you
know an ex developer with this much
experience and i know how to solve this
problem and kind of coming in with yes i
have these skills and how do they
translate here i would just say that
that's kind of like always the unifying
characteristic for good engineers and
then depending on the specific problems
that
the team or the business is trying to
solve at a given point in time that's
when you kind of want to delve into
more specialized skill sets so
typically
the skills that we kind of want to hire
for at render are not that different
from what i would have hired for on my
old dream at stripe i think the
difference is a little more on the
adjacent sides where i also actually
think that we could have used some of
those skills on my old team and a couple
of examples are design so you know
having like dedicated designers which we
did not have on my whole team we kind of
like you know consulted with the striped
design team but we didn't have like an
embedded designer a ux engineer so
people are actually thinking deeply
about the user experience and the
workflow we did not have that we
actually had a few people who were very
talented at that without their training
but just were like full staff engineers
and then a couple of other things that i
if i were to go back in time was a
dedicated support team so we have that
at render because you know and that's
kind of where the difference comes in of
being an internal versus a public
platform so at stripe it was actually
the engineers on the team that would act
as support on the rotation basically and
at render we also have that rotation
where actually everyone participates in
support but there's a steady team and
then a rotation both i think that's the
key difference is you kind of go deep on
special skill sets typically user facing
skill sets on a public platform which
you don't do on an internal platform but
actually having seen both i think that
some of these deeper expertise areas
could actually be taken back to internal
platform teams and they could actually
benefit from those
i mean when you think of uh internal
teams at any company they sound like
they should be different but you kind of
are saying like you really should treat
it more like a product more like
something you are shipping to customers
even if it's internal i think we'd have
happier users if you did that i also
wondered too when you first started at
stripe how large was the compute team's
team it was pretty small actually if i
remember correctly it was just around 14
people so we were just starting to split
the team so i kind of came in inherited
one half of the team one half of compute
which we called cloud which was the
layer that worked with the cloud
providers and the other half was called
deploy an orchestration set manager
deploy workflow and also orchestration
layer so we cannot like split it between
i believe six and eight people between
those two teams and i started with that
and then i think by the time i left it
was like you know four teams and a
little over 40 people
and looking at
how
things were managed when you first
started versus when you finish as well
as how things look at render i wonder
how you approach the process of running
a compute team or running an
infrastructure team as it grows
i think a few things i've kind of
learned is because i kind of got to see
things at a larger scale things like i
have a kind of like you know somewhat of
a foreshadowing of oh this is you know
we are going to be hitting scale limits
or reliability limits or even on the
people's side of like you know this kind
of experience of when to start splitting
the teams like you know what makes a
good size team versus what kind of
doesn't so there's a bit of things that
have kind of leaned on from my previous
experience like such as you know instant
management
thinking about reliability and thinking
about incidents and learning from
incidents and actually being proactive
about those which i think are typically
will take
larger companies like there's like
almost like a certain point in their
life
how when they start learning about it i
like to think that maybe because of my
experience of seeing it at a larger
scale i have learned to kind of you know
start sooner than absolutely need it but
that kind of thing benefits us there's
an element of also like you know just
ecosystem experience that kind of comes
in like you know vendors and like who do
our users care about that comes with
having done it at a slightly different
scale you mentioned how
when the company is large you built out
this formal process for incident
management and things like that i wonder
if there's anything else you can think
of that is typically in place at a large
organization that you think would really
benefit a small one i think
observability
is another one because that kind of goes
hand in hand with reliability and
incidents which are where i think that
more sas companies typically wait wait
longer to kind of you know build out
robust observability and i wouldn't say
that we are there yet either
i think we are still getting there
there's this kind of intangible just
being really really good operationally
that companies learn as they grow a lot
of it is stuff around incidence
reliability becoming much better about
observability better about like rigor
about stuff like this there's an element
of rigor around a quality that typically
comes in at larger companies but there i
actually was very pleasantly surprised
that render was already ahead of where i
expected it to be but just generalizing
i think that's typically not something
that smaller companies will invest in uh
security is another one like typically
companies wait a little longer to invest
in that i think smaller companies would
benefit from kind of you know getting
that expertise built in early especially
if you're like you know in a more
platform or enterprise product space
when you talk about
quality within the context of software
are you talking about code quality or
defects or you know what are you
referring to when you mention all of
them but like starting with like quality
right like you know
so when i say i was pleasantly surprised
i was i was pleasantly surprised to find
that as a default most coded renderer
gets reviewed there is a good trigger
around code reviews and feedback and
like you know thinking about code before
pushing it that's not just for like
quality but just also like you know for
learning and collaboration i think it's
just so powerful so that that was a good
thing but and then i think you know then
there's the defects and pushing it and
then at the other end of the defect
spectrum is the is the incident right
length basically incidents are basically
defects that are so critical that they
cause an incident so so it's that whole
spectrum between the writing of the code
to how you deal with incidents and and
operationalizing that entire
when you talk about improving quality a
lot of times that's related to making
sure things work whether they're tested
things like that in the case of a
platform as a service like render your
platform is running the software of
other people who software you don't
control right and i wonder if as a part
of your testing process how do you
account for that are you running random
applications against render things like
that i think we don't typically have to
do that just because you know there is
enough of an abstraction between what
our users are doing and what we are
doing that we don't have to worry about
that what does happen though there will
be an interesting series of support
questions that will often come in where
users are kind of struggling to deploy
something and it will not always be
clear whether the problem is in their
application or the library that they're
using or actually on render and that
gets tricky and actually interestingly
that is not unique to the public
platforms my old team at stripe had this
all the time as well where you know
people would come to the compute team
and ask for help debugging because they
had like you know literally gone through
the entire stack and often though like
you know try to debug and then kind of
uh we were like the last layer and we
would often end up helping them debug
their application problems versus it not
being an infrastructure problem so i
would say it doesn't it's not actually
something that we have to test as much
but it's something that we definitely
have to be prepared to answer questions
about and then often it is also like you
know there's always this interesting
kind of question like we might be able
to help them but also like you know what
is our level of obligation so we
generally try to be like good support
and to try to help them but there's also
like you know at some point we have to
also tell them like hey look actually
this is a problem with your application
and and you might need to fix it
it's a reminder that you aren't a
consulting service you're you're a
platform to host your application yeah
versus as an internal platform you often
cannot actually say no or like usually
people don't feel comfortable saying no
because in the end like you know you are
one larger team
and that's where the incentives are are
a little mixed let's say you're fielding
a support ticket for your internal team
and someone's saying i deployed this app
and it's not working would your support
team actually have to go in and look at
users code and things like that you mean
for the internal team right right right
yes yes and that was very often the case
and this was a mix of like you know
one is because you're part of the same
larger team you kind of have this
obligation to help your co-workers
and then the second problem is also
because you haven't typically had the
luxury of building those strong
interfaces
from the get go it's actually hard for
your users to know where the problem
lies
with a public platform you have built
strong enough abstractions that you can
quickly debug and tell your users that
hey know it shades it's there and this
is
exactly why we think it is with an
internal theme often the abstractions
are leaky
and it might not be easily
obvious and that's kind of where i was
alluding to the fact that internal
platform teams
could be likely better off if they had
those stronger abstractions and those
stronger boundaries could you give an
example of where
those boundaries leak in an internal
application one example is which was
kind of quite painful for my old team
was
we were using this service mesh library
called envoy
my team had kind of done the migration
kind of like rolled it out so all
internal service to service
communication was through onward because
onward provided you know stronger
security guarantees and more
observability
but when it was first rolled out it was
kind of you know one migrations are
always a bit rough so it was still new
so there were problems with the
migration itself
but then it kind of also led to this
narrative where a service would fall
over
people would quickly look at the logs
see an envoy log message somewhere far
down in the stack and be like hey
we have an envoy problem and my team
would then have to kind of debug it and
this is that same thing where like you
know the abstraction leaked because it
wasn't built to be strong there wasn't a
strong enough abstraction but then there
was also like this kind of problem of
guilt by association where you know we
would kind of end up debugging things or
have this problem and i think this is
just a very common problem for internal
infrastructure teams where they end up
debugging things across the stack yeah
that's really interesting because it's a
little counterintuitive where you would
think like oh we both know about this
thing so
you know it'll allow us to work better
together but in the case of
render or any other platform as a
service the user will never see the
envoy or they'll never see
all these things that are happening in
the background so they can't go to you
and say like well clearly it's your
problem right yeah and you also aren't
like sitting one desk over where you can
just be like tap on the shoulder and
you're like three levels of manager is
in the same manner
totally yeah so it's a culture thing
there too yeah yes absolutely
well i think that's basically everything
i had but is there anything else you
wanted to mention or that we should have
talked about one kind of pet hypothesis
that i could have liked to offer
because we talked about incidents and we
talked about computers
maybe there's kind of going to be this
expansion of products that are
essentially going to be replacements of
things that internal platform teams have
built over the years so i've kind of
like tweeted about this a bit in the
past but i think it's
it's my current pet theory about how
the platform as a service space is going
to expand we're on this current
evolution where all the developers that
work at large sas companies have gotten
used to a certain
set of tools
that they will now either build
themselves or like you know want to see
build and that's where the ecosystem
will kind of head next
so that's kind of i guess like one
hypothesis i would like to let out in
the wild
are you picturing something where
you know maybe five years from now or
something somebody would
go to render and they say i want to
build an application and render will
have like
here here's the way that you log in your
application and here's the dashboard you
plug in some maybe configuration and
we'll set it up for you you've already
picked these specific products i guess
or ways of doing the things that nearly
every application is already doing yes
yes i think for render's case that would
kind of be
a bit of the next step i think there's
also this element of
we kind of you know see
this next layer of basically like
platform as a service or like almost
like services as a services so so an
example would be you know we'll see more
managed database companies come up like
we are already in the space but that's
not our core competency but we'll see
more and more managed abs people will
push more and more stuff down
each large sas company has like
a whole plethora of internal tools that
they use and each of those is almost
like its own product
for instance and we will see more of
them kind of coming up and like you know
existing
where there will be a way to kind of you
know stitch together different tools and
provide them like say peer does or like
retool is trying to provide
or at the lesser kind of degree things
like you know
providing stock to compliance like this
it's now becoming like a product
or something so compliance is becoming
its own product right or
you're seeing companies exist that are
providing incident tooling specifically
so you have like jelly they're doing
like learning from incidents or you have
incident i o where they're like
providing instant management so all of
those will kind of you know become
stand-alone products in themselves
you know so you as a founder could take
out your credit card and sign up for
render plus
these two other tools and like you know
things that you would have done with
engineering effort will long be done
with you know your credit card well i
hope we get there because i think there
is so much
i suppose you could say brain energy
being used on every time somebody
creates a new application they have to
decide okay what are all the services
i'm going to use and what am i going to
do myself and if somebody could just
hand you hey use these things we've
configured them for you and you know
you're all set that could save so much
time yes yes i think that is 100
something like this kind of like a
startup kit of sas companies i've seen a
few of those actually floating around
already but i think
it will become more kind of canonical
at collide we know end users are it
admins most significant untapped
resources and key to solving the most
challenging to fix security issues
including instructing developers to set
passphrases on unencrypted ssh keys
finding plaintext two-factor backup
codes and teaching end users how to
store them securely convincing employees
to uninstall evil browser extensions
that may sell their browser history
visit collide.com sc radio to sign up
today that's
kolide.com
sc radio
enter your email when prompted to
receive your free collide gift bundle
after trial activation
you can try collide with all its
features on an unlimited number of
devices for free for 14 days no credit
card required try it out at collide.com
sc radio
to wrap up where can people find you
where can they find render and anything
like that go for it render.com check us
out there
or reach out to me on twitter i'm on
twitter if you can just like follow me
or reach out via dms also on linkedin if
you're more old school
cool well uma thank you so much for
joining me on software engineering radio
thank you so much for having me this was
a great conversation this has been
jeremy jung for software engineering
radio thanks for listening
[Music]
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter or through
our slack channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening